Raymond Cheng

CONTACT Information ryscheng@cs.washington.edu https://raymondcheng.net Networks Laboratory

Computer Science and Engineering

University of Washington

Box 352350

Seattle, WA 98195 USA

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research interests are in distributed systems and security, with a focus on cloud security and privacy. I am interested in building novel systems that broaden the rights of Internet users. These projects include privacy-preserving systems that give users better control over their data and systems that spread digital freedom of speech and information to citizens around the world.

EDUCATION

University of Washington, Seattle, WA

expected 2017

Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science and Engineering

- Thesis: Security and Privacy for Cloud Applications
- Advisor: Prof. Thomas Anderson and Prof. Arvind Krishnamurthy

M.S. in Computer Science

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

M.Eng. in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

2010

2009

- Thesis: WhanauSIP A Secure Peer-to-Peer Communications Platform
- Advisor: Prof. Frans Kaashoek and Dr. Chris Lesniewski-Laas

B.S. in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science

B.S. in Physics 2009

Professional Experience

National Security Agency

Maryland

 $Laboratory\ for\ Telecommunications\ Sciences$

Aug 2005 - Apr 2011

• Technical lead in a large program to secure critical telecommunications networks.

Microsoft Research Asia

Beijing, China

System Research Group, Dr. Lidong Zhou

Apr 2011 - Aug 2011

• Research Intern

Google

New York, NY

Search Quality, Michael Schueppert and Mayur Thakur

Jun 2012 - Sep 2012

• Software Engineer Intern

Google Ideas, Lucas Dixon and Jared Cohen

Sep 2014 - Jan 2015

• Software Engineer Intern

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

UW Computer Science and Engineering

• Distributed Systems (CSE452) Teaching Assistant (Thomas Anderson)

• Computer Systems (CSE550) Teaching Assistant (Arvind Krishnamurthy)

• Networks Seminar (CSE590L) Coordinator

• Robotics Systems Seminar (CSE590RS) Coordinator

UW Bioengineering Department

• Neural Engineering (BIOEN498C) Teaching Assistant (Albert Folch)

OPEN SOURCE PROJECTS

Talek

• Source Code: https://github.com/ryscheng/pdb

uProxy

• Website: uproxy.org

• Source Code: https://github.com/uProxy/uProxy

Radiatus

• Website: radiatus.io

• Source Code: https://github.com/freedomjs/radiatus

freedom.js

• Website: freedomjs.org

• Source Code: https://github.com/freedomjs/freedom

SERVICE

High School Outreach

Presented to high school students from around the country on the exciting possibilities of a career in computer science. Presentations included live demos and college advice.

- NEPA Girls Who Code, Scranton, PA.
- Delaware Valley H.S., Milford, PA
- UW CSE Open House, Seattle, WA
- Meadowdale H.S., Lynnwood, WA

Hackathon Mentorship

• Grace Hopper Open Source Day, Houston, TX

Oct 2015

NYUAD International Hackathon for Social Good in the Arab World, Abu Dhabi,
 UAE.

UW Science and Engineering Business Association (SEBA)

VP of Operations

2012-2015

- Managed the UW SEBA website, with > 20,000 page views per month.
- Managed the UW SEBA mentorship program, the largest science and engineering mentorship program on campus.

Refereed Publications

- [1] Cheng, R., Scott, W., Parno, B., Zhang, I., Krishnamurthy, A., Anderson, T. Talek: a Private Publish-Subscribe Protocol. In submission.
- [2] Cheng, R., Scott, W., Ellenbogen, P., Howell, J., Roesner, F., Krishnamurthy, A., and Anderson, T. Radiatus: a Shared-Nothing Server-Side Web Architecture. ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing (SOCC). 2016
- [3] Zhang, I., Lebeck, N., Fonseca, P., Holt, B., Cheng, R., Norberg, A., Krishnamurthy, A., Levy, H. Diamond: Automating Data Management and Storage for Wide-area, Reactive Applications. 11th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation (OSDI). 2016.
- [4] Bhoraskar, R., Langenegger, D., He, P., Cheng, R., Scott, W., and Ernst, M. User scripting on Android using BladeDroid. The 5th ACM SIGOPS Asia-Pacific Workshop on Systems (APSYS). 2014.
- [5] Cheng, R., Scott, W., Krishnamurthy, A., and Anderson, T. FreeDOM: a New Baseline for the Web. The 11th ACM Workshop on Hot Topics in Networks (HotNets XI). 2012.
- [6] Cheng, R., Hong, Ji., Kyrola, A., Miao, Y., Weng, X., Wu, M., Yang, F., Zhou, L., Zhao, F., and Chen, E. Kineograph: Taking the Pulse of a Fast-Changing and Connected World. Proceedings of the 7th ACM European Conference on Computer Systems (Eurosys). 2012.

TECHNICAL REPORTS

- [7] Scott, W., Cheng, R., Li, J., Krishnamurthy, A., and Anderson, T. Blocking-Resistant Network Services using Unblock. UW Technical Report UW-CSE-14-06-01. 2014.
- [8] Cheng, R., Schueppert, M., Becker, H., and Thakur, M. SolocoRank: Social Signals for Local Search Quality. UW Technical Report UW-CSE-13-11-05. 2013.
- [9] Scott, W., Cheng, R., Krishnamurthy, A., and Anderson, T. freedom.js: an Architecture for Serverless Web Applications UW Technical Report. UW-CSE-13-05-03. 2013.

PATENTS

[10] Yang, F., Zhou, L., Wu, M., Kyrola, A., Cheng, R., Miao, Y., Weng, X., and Hong, J. Platform for Continuous Graph Update and Computation. Patent Number 9244983. Microsoft Research, submitted 2011.

INVITED TALKS AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

[11] Radiatus: a Shared-Nothing Server-Side Web Architecture.

• SOCC: ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing. Santa Clara, CA. Oct 2016

- [12] uProxy: a Social Proxy for your Browser
 - Circumvention Tech Festival. Valencia, Spain. Mar 2015
 - TA3M. New York, NY.
 RIPE69. London, United Kingdom.
 Nov 2014
 Nov 2014
 - RIPE69. London, United Kingdom.

[13] User scripting on Android using BladeDroid

- APSYS: ACM Asia-Pacific Workshop on Systems. Beijing, China. Jun 2014
- Microsoft Research Asia. Beijing, China. Jun 2014

[14] uProxy: Crowdsourcing in the Face of Digital Repression

• Google Ideas Summit. New York, NY.

- Oct 2013
- YouTube. http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aGOXMRJWSeg

[15] FreeDOM: a New Baseline for the Web

• HotNets XI: Hot Topics in Networks. Redmond, WA.

Oct 2012

[16] Kineograph: Taking the Pulse of a Fast-Changing and Connected World

• Eurosys Conference. Bern, Switzerland.

Apr 2012 Apr 2012

• Stanford MobiSocial Seminar. Palo Alto, CA.

May 2012

[17] Donor Appreciation Speech

• Palantir. Palo Alto, CA.

• UW CSE Donor Luncheon. Seattle, WA.

Apr 2012

Press

uProxy

Select articles:

Google Unveils Tools to Access Web From Repressive Countries

http://business.time.com/2013/10/21/google-digital-rebels/

Google's uProxy: A Peer-to-Peer Gateway to Internet Freedom

http://mashable.com/2013/10/21/google-uproxy-internet-freedom/

Google announces uProxy: internet censorship avoidance in a browser extension http://www.engadget.com/2013/10/21/google-ideas-uproxy/

'Running battle': How Google hopes to beat countries cracking down on Internet freedom

 $http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/10/23/21080699-running-battle-how-google-hopes-to-beat-countries-cracking-down-on-internet-freedom$

Google uProxy lets you surf securely through a friends connection

http://www.geek.com/apps/google-uproxy-lets-you-surf-securely-through-a-friends-connection-1574584/

 $This\ Google\ Browser\ Extension\ Will\ Allow\ You\ To\ Bypass\ Internet\ Censorship\ http://www.fastcompany.com/3020362/fast-feed/this-google-browser-extension-will-allow-you-to-bypass-internet-censorship$

Google unveils services promoting free expression

http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/10/22/google-tools-idUSL1N0IB25B20131022 UW CSEs uProxy unveiled at Google Ideas Summit in NYC

http://news.cs.washington.edu/2013/10/22/uw-cses-uproxy-unveiled-at-google-ideas-summit-in-nyc/

Get round internet censors using a friend's connection

http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg22029415.500-get-round-internet-censors-using-a-friends-connection.html

FreeDOM

Congratulations to the winners of the Madrona Prize and the Peoples Choice Awards!

http://news.cs.washington.edu/2012/10/24/congratulations-to-the-winners-of-the-madrona-prize-and-the-peoples-choice-awards/

STUDENT ADVISING

• James Liu	2015-2016
• Elizabeth Wei	2014
• Bonnie Pan	2014
• Nick Martindell	2013-2014
• Paul Ellenbogen	2013-2014
• Tariq Yusuf	2012-2014
• Caylan Lee	2012-2013
• Nicholas Shahan	2012-2013

References

Thomas Anderson (tom@cs.washington.edu)

Warren Francis and Wilma Kolm Bradley Chair,
 Computer Science and Engineering, University of Washington

Jon Howell (jrh@google.com)

• Software Engineer, Google

Arvind Krishnamurthy (arvind@cs.washington.edu)

• Associate Professor, Computer Science and Engineering, University of Washington

Bryan Parno (parno@cmu.edu)

- Associate Professor, Computer Science Department, Carnegie Mellon University
- Researcher, Microsoft Research

Franziska Roesner (franzi@cs.washington.edu)

• Assistant Professor, Computer Science and Engineering, University of Washington

Additional references available upon request